Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Animation Number 4
Love
Single kanji A
Love takes away without reservation
Animation Number 4
Blue Scene
Animation Number 'none'
But...
Animation Number 8
But, humyan.
（ブラック羽川(はねかわ)）
いやにゃあ 人間
My myaster loves you.
俺の ご主人…
Solemn
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
There are people for whom it's impossible.
Animation Number 10
お前のことが
好きにゃんだにゃん
Animation Number 14
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
So if you fall in love with my myaster, I think that might bottle me up.
だからお前が ご主人と
恋仲(こいにゃか)に にゃってくれりゃあ
俺は引っ込むことが
できると思うんだが
Quit joking. Even I'm not gonna fall for that one.
（阿良々木(あららぎ)）
それは どういう冗談だ？
僕だって全てのボケに突っ込める
ってわけじゃないんだぞ
Plus, it's just terrible.
つうか冗談だとしても
悪質すぎるぞ
In this world, there are good lies and bad lies, and-
この世には ついていい嘘と
ついてダメな嘘が…
You really are stupid, humyan. Do you think I'm clever enough to lie to you?
（ブラック羽川）
バカだにゃあ 人間
俺に嘘をつけるようにゃ頭が
あると思うのか？
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
But, cat. If that's not a lie...
（阿良々木）
でっ でも 猫
そりゃ 嘘じゃないと
するんなら
お前の勘違いだよ
Aren't you just mistaken?
There's no way she could be in love with me.
そんなことが あるわけがない
Why do you think that? I wouldn't understand my myaster.
（ブラック羽川）
どうして そう思うにゃ？
俺が ご主人のことを
誤解するわけが にゃいにゃん
She's the only my myaster I have.
他にゃらぬ ご主人のこと
にゃんだからにゃ
But-
いや でも…
But even though she loves you, you're going out with someone else.
Animation Number 25
Restraint / Anger / Accumulation
（ブラック羽川）
だからよ
ご主人は
お前のことが好きにゃのに
お前は別の相手と
つきあってんだろ？
And showing it off in front of her.
そしてそれを まざまざと
（阿良々木）あ…
Documentary
（ブラック羽川）見せつけている
Animation Number 31
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
But Hanekawa isn't acting like that!
しかし羽川は
そんな素振り…
Headache didn't stop at all
Animation Number 33
If anything, she wants me to be with Senjougahara! She's even given me advice-
むしろ僕と
戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)のことを
It was getting just worse
Animation Number 36
応援してくれてる
感じっつうか
It was getting just worse
Animation Number 36
相談に乗ってくれたり…
It was getting just worse
Animation Number 36
That's exactly what has her so stressed, meow!
（ブラック羽川）
だからこそ
Animation Number 38
Disorder
Single kanji B
I feel... bad.
Animation Number 36
どんどんストレスが
溜まっていったんだにゃ
Do you think a girl like my myaster could work up the guts to ask you out?
お前よ ご主人の性格で
What have I done?
Animation Number 41
略奪愛にゃんて
できると思うのか？
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
She couldn't even let slip a single hint of it.
おくびにも出すわけが
にゃいんだにゃん
（阿良々木）ハア…
I don't know everything, I-
（阿良々木）
そんな 羽川が…
But, I had no way to tell that... If Hanekawa...
Animation Number 48
If that girl decided to hide her true feelings,
even Senjougahara wouldn't be able to figure her out
Animation Number 51
Documentary
Pressure
Single kanji C
But...
Animation Number 51
Am I... insensitive?
Animation Number 52
Then that talk about the future course...
Although partly due to Oshino's influence,
you can say that was Hanekawa Tsubasa's
grand journey of broken heart...
Then that talk about the future course...
Although partly due to Oshino's influence,
you can say that was Hanekawa Tsubasa's
grand journey of broken heart...
And she had headache too,
right after that career talk.
Animation Number 54
And,
Animation Number 56
Documentary
That time she closed her eyes and tried to kiss me...
Animation Number 58
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Wow, Hanekawa was-
Nisio Isin
Episode 15
Bakemono
gatari
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Typeface used for images: HGP mincho B
Tsubasa Cat, Part Five
Episode 15
Animation Number 62
Kawa
Single kanji D
Animation Number 62
Kawa
Single kanji D
Hanekawa Tsubasa is a very important person for me
Animation Number 62
Last Episode
How long?
（阿良々木）いつから… だ？
（ブラック羽川）あん？
How long has Hanekawa loved me?
（阿良々木）
羽川は いつから僕のことを？
Animation Number 68
Obey
Single kanji E
Spring break
Animation Number 88
Since spring break.
（ブラック羽川）
春休みからだにゃ
REMINISCENCE
From episode 1, animation number 25
I guess my myaster thought the humyan/vyampire relationship thing was the purrfect thing
ご主人にとって
人間と吸血鬼の物語は
REMINISCENCE
From episode 1, animation number 54
いかにも荒唐無稽で
REMINISCENCE
From episode 1, animation number 59
to break her free from the life she was sick of.
自身の置かれている立場を
打破してくれるパワーを
持っていそうにも見えただろうにゃ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's-
打破なんて…
But she never would have expected a rival to appear, meow.
（ブラック羽川）
でも ご主人は
ライバルの出現にゃんて
まるで 予想だに
してにゃかったんだよにゃ
Meanwhile, the girl you're going out with moved in lightning-fast.
そこへいくと
お前が今 付き合ってる女(おんにゃ)は
電光石火だったよにゃ
REMINISCENCE
From episode 5, animation number 233
Purple Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That time, Hanekawa...
Animation Number 80
Was happy for me.
That's what I thought
Animation Number 82
But...
Animation Number 83
Was that a lie too?
Animation Number 84
（羽川）
私 嘘なんか
ついたことがないもの
Animation Number 86
I never lie.
I
n
e
v
r
l
i
e
I never lie
Wrong.
（阿良々木）
違う　だとすれば
お前の言うことは
If this is true, you've told nothing but lies, Hanekawa Tsubasa!
嘘ばっかりだ 羽川翼(つばさ)！
Following, a performance of troupe Dog Curry
Animation Number 93
A girl raised in a cold, unloving family.
（ブラック羽川）
冷めた家庭に育った女の子
During her spring break,
彼女が春休みに
衝撃的にゃ出会いをした—
she has a shocking encounter with a supernyatural entity who happens to be a classmate.
非日常の存在は同級生だった
It feels like fate. Her heart begins to stir.
運命的にゃものを感じる
ほのかに募る恋心
Then, later, he saves her life-she's convinced that it's love.
そして今度は自らの命を助けられ
恋は確信へと変わる
Or something.
End of performance
Animation Number 94
とか ニャハハハハ
にゃんつって
Whether she's right or wrong, she feels like she's had something purrecious snatched away from her.
見事にというか無様にというか
とんびに油揚げを
さらわれた格好にゃ
（阿良々木）あ…
Wait, cat. There's something not quite right there.
いや 猫 ちょっと待てよ
それって おかしくないか？
Even if I'm the source of her stress like you're saying, that wouldn't be enough to release you.
確かに お前の言うとおり
僕がストレスの原因だったとして
それだけでは お前は
出てこないだろ
There must be something else big that's stressing her out.
他にも有力なストレッサーが…
Wrong. It's all you.
違うにゃ　お前のことだけにゃ
But aren't you the embodiment of all the stress Hanekawa built up from her home life?
でも お前は羽川が家族のことで
ずっと積み重ねてきた
ストレスの権化なのだろ？
Just a couple months of love shouldn't-
そのお前が
たかが数か月の恋愛のことで…
"Just"?
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（ブラック羽川）
〝たかが〞？
（阿良々木）あ…
And just what makes you think a few months of lovesickness
10数年積み重ねてきた
家族の苦しさが
Embryo
Animation Number 109
29th day
can't be worse than over a decade of family problems, meow?
数か月 募らせた恋愛の切にゃさに
劣っちゃいけない理由でも
あるのかにゃ！
Back to the belly
Animation Number 113
What, haven't you ever really fallen for anyone?
お前 ひょっとして
真剣に人を好きににゃったこととか
ねえんじゃ にゃいのか？
（阿良々木）な…
Are you just dating that girl to shut her up?
今 その女と
付き合ってることだって
ただ単に押し切られた
だけじゃにゃいの？
You may as well dump her and get with my myaster, then.
だとしたら さっさと別れて
ご主人と付き合ってやれば
いいにゃん
I can't do that, cat.
でも それはできないよ 猫
Oh? Why not? Don't you need to reward my myaster for everything she's done for you?
（ブラック羽川）
あん？ どうしてにゃ？
お前 ここは ご主人の恩義に
報いるべきじゃ にゃいのか？
If I did that, Hanekawa would just be taking advantage of my debt to her.
（阿良々木）
それをやると 羽川に恩に対して
つけ込ませることになってしまう
I don't want to let her do that kind of thing.
羽川に そんなことは させられない
No, that's not it. That's just a convenient excuse.
いや 違うな
これは都合のいい言い訳だ
I can't deny my feelings for Senjougahara.
単純に僕の戦場ヶ原に対する
気持ちを偽ることは できない
I figured you'd go for Hanekawa-san between the two of them.
REMINISCENCE
New footage for episode 15, animation number 130.
（八九寺(はちくじ)）
いや 普通 あの２人だったら
羽川さんのほうを
選ぶんじゃないかと思いまして
Animation Number 131
Connection
Single kanji F
You are wrong, Hachikuji
Animation Number 131
Even with how she acts sometimes, I still love Senjougahara.
（阿良々木）
僕は あの性格を含めて
戦場ヶ原のことが好きなんだ
Yes
Animation Number 135
I love everything
There's nothing I don't love about her
Animation Number 135
She's the first woman I've ever really loved.
生まれて初めて
真剣に人を好きになったんだよ
（ブラック羽川）
ふ〜ん　そうかにゃ
Oh, is that so?
Plus, cat.
（阿良々木）それにさ 猫
No matter the circumstances, it's Hanekawa's own weakness that brought you forth.
事情は どうあれ
お前を出したのは羽川の弱さなんだ
Denial/Voice/Line
Animation Number 144
What you told me is something Hanekawa should have told me herself.
さっきの言葉は お前じゃなくて
羽川が僕に言うべき言葉だった
She's just forcing you to do the hard part.
苦しい役目を
お前に押し付けたにすぎない
Denial/Voice/Line
Animation Number 147
There are plenty of people who've lived through the same problems Hanekawa is having
羽川と同じ環境でだって
怪異(かいい)に頼らず
自分 一人で その環境を
生き抜いているヤツもいるはずさ
without relying on an aberration.
Her just relying on you is an insult to each one of them.
羽川が お前みたいなのに
頼ったのは
そういう連中に対する冒涜(ぼうとく)だ
Denial/Voice/Line
Animation Number 148
You've got some nerve to say that, meow. Oh well, I guess you've earned the right.
言うじゃにゃいか
まあ お前には
それを言う資格はあるんだろうよ
After all, you're the guy so kindhearted he'd even sacrifice himself to save a mortally-wounded vyampire.
REMINISCENCE
From episode 1, animation number 20
お前は我が身を犠牲にして
ひん死の吸血鬼を
助けてしまうくらいの
お人よしにゃんだからにゃ
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
If you're kind to everyone, that means no humyan is special.
誰にでも優しいっていうのは
特別にゃ人間がいにゃい
ってことだにゃ
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
Animation Number 158
I understand that because my myaster was kind to everyone, too.
ご主人も誰にでも優しかったから
俺には それが分かるにゃ
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（ブラック羽川）
フン じゃあ まあ
しかたにゃいか
Oh well, there's no changing someone's feelings.
人の気持ちを変えることは
できにゃいにゃ
I learned that last time. Learned it quite well, meow.
それは前回 よく学(まにゃ)んでいるにゃ
学んで懲りているにゃん
That's good.
（阿良々木）そりゃ 助かるよ
I guess Hanekawa feels the same way, then?
しかし やっぱり
羽川も そうなのかな
Then I might have been a bit harsh scolding her like that.
だとしたら さっきみたいに
責めるようなことを言うのは
酷なのかもしれないな
あん？ 何(にゃん)の話だにゃ？
What do you mean?
Well... Vampires have a special charisma, right?
（阿良々木）いや その話だよ
吸血鬼の特性に
魅了ってのがあって
And because of it I've been popular with the girls since spring break. Hanekawa told me that.
それで春休み以降 僕は女の子に
モテモテになっているって話
羽川から聞いたんだぜ？
Hanekawa's always so serious. If she's so caught up in her feelings, she must  have been a victim of that.
羽川は真面目なヤツだから
それで思いつめちゃった
っていうんなら
100パーセント 被害者だよな
と思ってさ
Wait, why did you stop talking?
どうした 急に黙り込んで
No, you're wrong.
いや それは違うにゃ
（阿良々木）え？
A knockoff vyampire like you can't use his charismya at all.
お前みたいにパチモンの吸血鬼には
魅了は使えにゃいにゃ
But...
（阿良々木）でも…
The power of charismya isn't a love potion like that, anyway.
（ブラック羽川）
大体 魅了ってのは
そんにゃ惚れ薬みたいにゃ
能力じゃにゃいにゃん
It's the power to completely remove their will, purroducing nothing more than your very own marionette.
自意識を消失
ただの操り人形を作る能力にゃん
Marionette?
（阿良々木）操り人形？
Not just infatuate them?
虜じゃないのか？
Well, just think, humyan. Are any of the girls you know what you'd call "completely obedient"?
（ブラック羽川）例えば 人間
お前の周りの女の子は
お前の言うことに絶対服従するか？
Is there anyone who'll do anything you say, with no questions asked?
何ひとつ逆らうことにゃく
お前の言うとおりに
動くヤツがいるか？
Crab
Snail
Monkey
Snake
Cat
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Not a one.
（阿良々木）
そんなヤツは １人もいねえな
えっ じゃあ…
Then...
Sorry, I'm just teasing.
（羽川）ごめんね
今 私
意地悪なこと 言ったよね
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）ああ そういうこと
That must have been-
Was that a lie?
Animation Number 190
A lie better kept unsaid
A painful wish
Animation Number 191
There's no changing someone's feelings.
（ブラック羽川）
人の気持ちは変えられにゃい にゃ
But that's not like my myaster at all.
しかし にゃるほど　そりゃ まあ
ご主人らしくも にゃかったにゃ
フン 俺は嘘をつく頭が にゃいから
バラしちゃったにゃ
I guess I gave it away by being too dumb to lie, meow.
Maybe that's another hard part she forced you to do.
（阿良々木）
それもまた つらい役目を
押し付けたってことに
なるんだろうな
I guess I should be proud that Hanekawa loves me.
じゃあ 僕は誇っていいんだな
羽川に
好きになってもらえたことを
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Anyway, we need to find Shinobu.
まあ とりあえずは
忍(しのぶ)を探さないとな
Now that I think of it, no one I asked to help has gotten back to me yet.
そういや 協力してもらってる
みんなからの連絡もないし
I should probably tell Sengoku to call it off soon.
ああ そろそろ千石(せんごく)のヤツには
撤収命令を出さないと
にゃあ 人間
Hey, humyan.
There's one other way.
もう１つ あるんだがにゃ
（阿良々木）うん？
A way to confine me again without relying on a vyampire.
吸血鬼に頼らず 俺を迅速に
効率よく引っ込める策
How?
どういう策だ？
Why don't you walk on over to that streetlight?
お前 ちょっと歩くにゃん
その街灯の下 辺りまで
（阿良々木）うん？
こうか？
Like this?
A little bit further, meow. You're right under it, so you don't have enough of a shadow there.
ああ もうちょっと前にゃ
そこだと真下に にゃっちゃうから
影が出にゃいにゃん
Shadow?
（阿良々木）影？
Tsubasa Cat Ep 5
ニャハ
A beginning
Animation Number 255
（阿良々木）ぐああああ！
Documentary
Spirit
あ… 猫 てめえ…
Cat, you-
Solemn
I told you I didn't just come here to make friends.
（ブラック羽川）
だからよ 慣(にゃ)れたつもりに
にゃってんじゃねえって
言ったろ？
I'm not pathetic enough yet to want to be friendly with a human.
人間にゃんかと
和気あいあいとするほど
俺は落ちぶれちゃ いにゃいんだよ
What do you think this will accomplish?!
こんなことをして
どうなるってんだ
I told you I had another plan, meow.
だから もう１つの策にゃ
I don't need to be here if the source of her stress-you-is gone.
ストレスの本体である お前が
いにゃくにゃってしまえば
俺が いる必要も
にゃくにゃるんにゃ
（阿良々木）く…
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
そっ そんな…
That's-
こっ 懲りたんじゃねえのかよ
Haven't you learned?!
When you attacked Hanekawa's parents during Golden Week...
ゴールデンウィークに
羽川の両親を襲って
Just doing that won't solve anything!
それだけじゃ済まなかっただろうが
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
く… お前は消えずに さらに
町の人を襲ってたじゃないか
You didn't go away! You started attacking passersby!
REMINISCENCE
From episode 11, animation number 263
Human stress isn't that simple!
だから人間のストレスは
そんな単純なものじゃ…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I failed that time. I didn't kill her parents, meow.
（ブラック羽川）
俺の あのときの失敗は
ご主人の両親を
殺さにゃかったことにあるにゃ
I've learned. I won't make the same mistake twice.
それに俺は懲りた
同じ轍(てつ)は二度と踏まにゃい
（阿良々木）あ…
I will certainly kill you.
（ブラック羽川）確実に殺す
Kill
Animation Number 260
I will certainly kill you
CERTAINLY KILL
Animation Number 260
Kill...
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）
殺す…
But that's Hanekawa's inner thoughts.
（阿良々木）
でも それもまた羽川の裏面で
羽川の言葉でもあるんだ
Hanekawa's words.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I owe Hanekawa my life. I'd do anything for her.
命の恩人
羽川のためなら
僕は何だってする
You should be happy. You get to ride my myaster's naughty body straight to Heaven.
（ブラック羽川）
まあ 幸せに思えよ
ご主人の いやらしい体に抱かれて
昇天できるんだからにゃ
（阿良々木）あ… ハア
I'm dying for Hanekawa's sake.
（阿良々木）
羽川のために死ねるのなら…
Hitagi
Animation Number 272
ぐっ がはっ
No! I can't!
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）
いや ダメだ！
If Hanekawa kills me, Senjougahara will kill her for sure!
羽川が僕を殺せば
戦場ヶ原は確実に羽川を殺す
So I can't die!
だからそれは ダメだ
That's the absolute worst way to handle it!
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
これは最低
最悪の手段だ
はっ 放せ！
Let me go!
（ブラック羽川）あん？
Just let me go!
とにかく放せ！
Pleading for your life?
命乞いかにゃん？ それもいいにゃ
Very well. If you promise you'll be my myaster's lover, I'll let you go.
もしも 今からでも
ご主人と付き合うって言うんにゃら
放してやっても いいにゃん
ぐ… だから それは無理だって
I told you, I can't!
You sure did.
だろうにゃ
Well, then.
（ブラック羽川）じゃあ もういい
Die.
お前 死ねよ
それとも誰かに
助けでも求めてみるかにゃ？
Or maybe you could try calling for someone to help?
You've helped plenty of people, maybe one of them will return the favor.
今まで さんざん いろんにゃヤツを
助けてきたお前にゃ
誰かが助けてくれるかも
しれにゃいにゃ
One of them...
（阿良々木）誰かって…
Mayoi
Animation Number 299
No one's going to save me.
助けなんて無理だ
No one? Why?
（ブラック羽川）
無理？ どうして
People just accept help selfishly, for their own sake.
だって 人は１人で
勝手に助かるだけだから
You don't really think that, do you?
それは
お前の意見じゃにゃいだろう？
It's just something you say.
それは ただの言葉だ
お前の気持ちじゃにゃい
It's not how you feel, meow.
The question's how you really feel.
問題は お前が
どういう気持ちでいるのか にゃ
Suruga
Animation Number 306
Maybe people do just accept help selfishly for their own sake-
（ブラック羽川）
そりゃ 人は１人で
勝手に助かるだけだけれど
but what does that have to do with the reasons their helper has?
助ける側に そんにゃ事情が
関係あるのかにゃ？
Animation Number 308
Nadeko
How many people do you think want to help you?
お前を助けたいと思っているヤツが
一体 どれだけいると思っている？
Are you rejecting every one of them?
それを お前は１人残らず
拒否するのかにゃあ
They'd be sad, wouldn't they.
（阿良々木）
やっぱり悲しむだろうな
Hanekawa and Senjougahara...
羽川も 戦場ヶ原も 神原(かんばる)も
Kanbaru and Sengoku, too.
Circles
on water
Animation Number 315
千石も 八九寺だって
ひょっとしたら…
Even Hachikuji.
For example, if I died
Animation Number 315
If I...
Save... me...
（阿良々木）助けて…
Save me...
助けて 忍
Shinobu!
Animation Number 320
にゃあああ！
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You don't have enough of a shadow there.
Black Hanekawa/Reminiscence/Voice-only
Animation Number 343
（ブラック羽川）
そこだと真下に
にゃっちゃうから
影が出にゃいにゃん
（阿良々木）ああ…
That's enough! Stop, Shinobu!
そろそろ やめろ
やめてくれ 忍！
If you go any further, you'll kill Hanekawa too. I don't want that.
それ以上 吸ったら
羽川まで いなくなってしまう
それは嫌だ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Araragi-kun...
阿良々木くん
（阿良々木）あ…
Don't say lonely things like, "I care more about my debt to you than our friendship."
私との友情よりも
私に恩返しをすることのほうが
ずっと大事だなんて
そんな寂しいこと言わないでよ
（阿良々木）ああ
Be nice, Araragi-kun.
阿良々木くん きちんとしなさい
Okay.
はい
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Come on, onii-chan, it's morning!
（火憐(かれん)）兄ちゃん！ 朝だぞ こら！
You need to get up!
（月火(つきひ)）
いい加減に起きないとダメだよ
Come on !
もう！
ぐわ！
After that, Kanbaru, who had come to check up on us, helped me and Hanekawa home.
（阿良々木）
あのあと 僕と羽川は
あの場に駆けてきた神原の助けで
家に帰った
And that day, before school, I went to the ruined cram school.
そして その日 僕は学校に行く前に
学習塾跡へと向かった
To bring Shinobu, still hidden in my shadow, back to Oshino.
あれから僕の影に
潜みっぱなしの忍を
忍野(おしの)のもとへと
送り届けるためだ
But...
でも…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
GRAND CULTURAL FESTIVAL
（阿良々木）おっ
（阿良々木）フッ
You're late.
遅かったね
I had to stop for something.
寄り道してたもんでな
How are you feeling?
元気？
Great.
超元気
Good morning.
おはよう
I don't know yet how much Hanekawa remembers.
（阿良々木）
羽川に どのくらいまでの記憶が
残っているのかを
僕は まだ知らない
I need to ask her someday, but not now.
いつかは聞かなくては
ならないことだが
それは今では ないだろう
Hanekawa needs time to mend her heart, too.
羽川にも心の整理整頓をする時間が
必要なはずである
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Hitagi
Animation Number 432
（阿良々木）おっ
Welcome back.
おかえりなさい
I'm back.
ただいま
You get to plan our next date.
今度のデートは 阿良々木くんが
プランニングしなさい
（阿良々木）え？
If you bring me somewhere weird, I'll flay you.
変なところに連れて行ったら
皮を剥ぐわよ
Sure.
了解
I'm cool with that.
（阿良々木）
望むところだ
This time, I'll show you my treasure.
戦場ヶ原に今度は僕の宝物を
見せてやろう
Someday even crabs need to start on a journey.
いつか 蟹(かに)も食べにいかなくちゃ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I had Kanbaru wait for us, and after school she,
放課後 僕は戦場ヶ原と羽川
それから待ってもらっていた
神原を連れて
Senjougahara, Hanekawa, and I went back to the ruined cram school.
再度 学習塾跡へと向かった
One day, I'll leave this city.
（忍野）
いつかは僕も この町を出ていく
Now I understand.
（阿良々木）
今なら分かる
昨日 ここを訪れた際
When I came here yesterday...
Oshino was outside getting ready to move on.
忍野が野外に出ていたのは
あれは撤収作業の最中だったのだ
I won't just disappear without telling you.
（忍野）
ある日 突然 あいさつも無しで
姿を消したりは しないさ
I'm an adult, so I at least know to do that.
僕も大人だからね
そこら辺は わきまえてる
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Why didn't I realize?
（阿良々木）
どうして気付かなかった
That line itself just had to have been a farewell.
あのセリフそのものが
どうしようもないくらいに
もう別れのあいさつじゃないか
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
He's the kind of person who never says goodbye.
別れの言葉を決して口にしない
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That awkward man who hates farewells more than anything...
人との別れが何より苦手な
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
あの不器用な男の
精一杯の親愛の証
It shows just how deeply he cared about me.
Koyomi/Monologue/Line
Animation Number 475
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
When I went searching for for Shinobu, he let the meddlecat free on purpose, and left this place behind.
あいつは僕が
忍を探しに飛び出したときに
障(さわ)り猫(ねこ)を わざと見逃して
ここを後にしたのだろう
Because he believed I could handle Shinobu and Hanekawa myself.
忍のことも
羽川のことも
僕が１人で何とかできると
そう確信して
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Man, he really was.
まったく あれだよな
Yeah, he was.
そうね あれだわ
Definitely.
あれだよね 実際
He sure was.
うん あの人は あれに違いない
A nice guy.
（一同）お人よし
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I may meet more aberrations in the future.
（阿良々木）
これからも僕は怪異に遭うだろう
But that's okay.
でも大丈夫だ　僕は知っている
Now I know.
There's dark places in this world, and things that live in them.
この世に闇があり
そこに住む者がいることを
Even within my own shadow.
例えば僕の影の中にも住んでいる
The culture festival finally starts tomorrow.
明日は いよいよ文化祭だった
Our class project is-
僕たちのクラスの出し物は
a haunted house.
お化け屋敷
Tsubasa Cat, Part Five
Cat
Bakemonogatari
With that...
End
That's Deneb, Altair, Vega
are ga DENEBU ARUTAIRU BEGA
the summer triangle that you pointed out.
kimi wa yubisasu natsu no daisankaku
So remember
oboete
to look at the sky.
sora wo miru
I finally found you, Altair,
yatto mitsuketa orihimesama
though where are you, Vega?
dakedo doko darou hikoboshisama
This is loneliness.
kore ja hitoribocchi
I looked up from the pitch-dark world.
makkura no sekai kara miageta
The stars fell in the night sky, and
yozora wa hoshi ga furu you de
just when was it from?
itsu kara darou
That I, who ran after you,
kimi no koto wo
was there.
oikakeru watashi ga ita
Please heed my wish.
douka onegai
Don't be surprised.
odorokanaide
Listen
kiite yo
to these feelings
watashi no
of mine.
kono omoi wo